本剧改编自圣经  它们曾改变世界
本剧将始终保持《圣经》真谛
《圣经》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
犹太王国是由伟大的英雄们一手建立
Great heroes have forged the Jewish nation in faith.
梅瑟解放了子民  带他们摆脱埃及人的奴役
Moses freed the people from Egyptian slavery.
上主啊
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
若苏厄带领他的人民进入盟约之地
Joshua led them into the promised land.
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
达味团结以色列人
David united the Israelites...
夺下了耶路撒冷
and delivered the city of Jerusalem.
但如今他们的后裔由罗马统治
But now their descendants are ruled by Rome...
臣服于般雀·比拉多之下
under Pontius Pilate.
罗马人渣  罗马强盗
Roman scum! Roman thieves!
数百人正要去见比拉多长官
Hundreds are heading to see the Prefect Pilate.
什么
What?
他们还未近他的身  就会成为亡魂
He'll have them cut down before they could get anywhere near him.
也该让你们知道你们的主人为你们做了什么
It's time you understood what your masters do for you.
比拉多残杀了成百上千的犹太人
Pilate has already massacred hundreds of Jewish people.
大司祭盖法深感再多的骚乱
High Priest Caiaphas feels any further disorder
只会让比拉多继续杀戮
could make Pilate kill again.
或者关闭圣殿
Or shut the temple.
在加里肋亚
In the province of Galilee,
耶稣已经引起轰动
Jesus has already been making waves.
倘若你饥渴慕义
If you hunger for righteousness,
跟随我  你们必要得饱饫
you will be filled... through me.
我听说了一个年轻先知
I've had a report of a young prophet,
纳匝肋人耶稣
Jesus of Nazareth.
在加里肋亚  有很多人跟从他
He has a big following in Galilee.
他能创造奇迹
He works miracles.
耶稣为村民驱魔
Jesus has cast out demons,
治疗疾病
cured the sick...
甚至能起死回生
and has even raised the dead.
很多人都相信  他就是默西亚
Thousands believe he is the Messiah.
他们希望你能做他们的君王
They want you to be their king,
犹太人的王
king of the Jews.
你能像带领军队一般引领我们
You can lead us like an army.
动用武力不是解决办法
This is not the way, not by force.
耶稣和他的跟随者
Now Jesus and his followers...
正前往权力的中心--耶路撒冷 前进
are heading to the center of power- Jerusalem.
加里肋亚默西亚的出现
The Messiah from Galilee
和耶路撒冷逾越节的时间如此接近
and Jerusalem of Passover have time near.
比拉多知道吗
Does Pilate know?
圣经
主日
逾越节前一周
逾越节是犹太人一年中最重要的节日
Passover is the biggest Jewish festival of the year.
成千上万的人来到耶路撒冷感谢天主
Thousands come to Jerusalem to thank God...
解救他们的祖先摆脱埃及人的奴役
for releasing their ancestors from Egyptian slavery.
看  是耶稣  默西亚
Look! It's Jesus! The Messiah!
带上棕树枝  默西亚  默西亚
Bring those palms! Messiah! Messiah!
耶稣进城在群众中掀起了狂潮
Jesus ' entrance creates a storm.
他在那儿  他来了 贺三纳 贺三纳
There he is! There he is! Hosanna! Hosanna!
贺三纳  贺三纳
Hosanna! Hosanna!
先知匝加利亚曾预言  犹太人的新王
The prophet Zechariah predicted that a new king of the Jews...
将骑着驴进城
would enter the city on a donkey.
贺三纳
Hosanna!
贺三纳  贺三纳
Hosanna! Hosanna!
他现在在哪儿
Where is he now?
他刚骑着驴进了城
He's just entered the city on a donkey.
瞧  你们的君王来了
See, your king comes to you,
一身正气  凯旋而来  而且谦卑有礼
righteous and victorious, humble...
还是骑着驴进城的
and riding on a donkey.
他往哪里去了
Where is he headed?
朝圣殿去了
Towards the temple.
这个来自加里肋亚的扰乱者是个麻烦
This agitator from Galilee- he's trouble.
群众呢  有什么反应
The crowds- how are they responding?
罗马人呢  有采取行动吗
And the Romans, have they made any move yet?
-没有  -迟早的事罢了
-No. -Hmm. Well, so far.
决不能让他在逾越节捣乱
He must not interfere with Passover.
天主会将他的忿怒降在所有人身上
God will bring his wrath down upon all of us.
如果群众失控
And... who knows what Pilate will do...
谁知道比拉多会做出什么
if the crowds run out of control.
尼苛德摩  和玛耳曷一起去
Nicodemus, go with Malchus.
如果他进入圣殿  好好看着他
If he enters the temple, watch him.
好好看着
Do not blink.
我要知道一切情况  去吧
I need to know everything. Go.
感谢YYETS字幕组
原始翻译时间轴及制作
天主教长沙青年团体重制
本字幕采用天主教思高译本
仅供福传学习
禁止用于任何商业盈利行为
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!
天国就要来了
The kingdom is coming!
天国就要来了  这可是默西亚
The kingdom is coming! Messiah!
那是巴辣巴
That's Barabbas.
默西亚
Messiah!
以色列的君王
King of Israel,
你为什么不解救我们
why don't you make us free?
主啊  拯救我们远离罗马人
Save us from the Romans, Lord.
我们带着和平而来  巴辣巴
We come in peace, Barabbas.
贺三纳  贺三纳
Hosanna! Hosanna!
让开
Move.
闪开
Get out of the way!
退开
Get back!
圣殿是圣经之中最为神圣的地方
The temple is the holiest place in the Bible.
在节日里
During festival times,
买卖献祭的动物和兑换银钱的交易
selling sacrificial animals and changing money...
十分兴旺
has become a thriving business.
我来换换你这儿的钱
Change your money here!
二  五
Two, five-
都来这换吧
All change here!
换钱的到这里
Exchange here!
你在干什么
What are you doing?
耶稣  别这样
Jesus, please.
经上不是记载说
Is it not written-
慢着
Wait.
经上不是记载说
Is it not written-
"我的殿宇...
"My house-"
"我的殿宇应称为祈祷之所"吗
"My house shall be called the house of prayer"?
但是你们
But you,
你们竟把它做成了贼窝
you have made it a den of thieves.
你是谁  有何资格这样说教我们
Who are you to tell us this?
教法律的是我们  而不是你
We teach the law, not you.
你们只为身份高贵者祈祷
You pray lofty prayers...
在圣殿之中装出虔诚的模样
and love your shows of piety in the temple.
假善的人啊
Hypocrites.
你们不能事奉天主
You cannot serve God...
又事奉金钱
and money.
这太可恶了
This is outrageous.
你们却什么忙都帮不上
And you were little help.
他很聪明
He's clever.
民众都尊崇他
The crowd worship him.
他有点不寻常
There is something unusual about him.
没什么不寻常的
There is nothing unusual about him,
除了有搞破坏的本事之外
apart from his ability to cause havoc.
如果他回来了  向他挑战
If he returns, challenge him.
让他的追随们瞧瞧  他们的默西亚
Make his supporters see their Messiah...
是个头脑多么简单的乡下人
for the simpleminded peasant that he is.
星期一
距逾越节四天
逾越节前的一星期
In the week leading up to Passover,
犹太朝圣者们每天都来圣殿朝拜
Jews pilgrims visit the temple daily.
为穷人们捐钱吧
Ounce for the poor.
天主保佑你
God bless you!
耶稣也回来了
Jesus also returns,
告诫更多的人
to preach to ever larger crowds.
骆驼穿过针孔
It's much harder for a rich person
比富有的人
to enter the kingdom of God,
进天主的国
than it is,
还要容易
for a carmel to go through the eye of a needle.
最重要的是
The most important thing...
你应该像爱你自己一样
is that you should love your neighbor...
爱你的近人
as you love yourself.
辣彼
Teacher!
他们说你学识渊博  那么告诉我们
They say you are learned. So tell us.
我们应该向罗马人交税吗
Should we pay taxes to the Romans?
不
No!
圈套
It's a trap.
辣彼
Well, teacher,
我们应该向罗马人交税吗
should we... pay the Romans taxes...
不交  不交
Not pay! Not pay!
不交
Not pay!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
以色列
Israel!
告诉他
Tell him!
这肖像和名号是谁的
Whose face is on the coin?
是凯撒的
Caesar's.
那么凯撒的
Then give to Caesar...
就应归还凯撒
what is Caesar's...
天主的
and give to God...
就应归还天主
what is God's.
大司祭  那个跟耶稣在一起的人
High Priest, that man there with Jesus,
他来找过我
he approached me.
他想帮我们
He wants to help us.
真的吗  或许真用得上
Really? That could be useful.
你让他占了上风
You let him get the better of you.
但我可能已经找到了对付他的办法
Yet I may have found a way to deal with him.
星期三
距逾越节两天
要顺从
Teachers of the law,
制定法律者
obey them.
凡他们对你们说的  你们要行要守
Do everything they tell you,
但不要照他们的行为去做
but don't do what they do.
因为他们只说不做
They don't practice what they preach.
他们所做的一切工作  都是为叫人看
Everything they do is done for others to see.
你们的父只有一位
You only have one father,
就是天上的父
and he is in heaven.
你们的导师只有一位
You only have one teacher,
他...
and he...
就是默西亚
is the Christ.
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
你看见这些雄伟的殿宇了吗
Do you see all these great buildings?
将来在这里决没有一块石头
Not one stone of this place,
留在另一块石头上，而不被拆毁的
not one stone, will be left standing.
他说他要拆毁圣殿
He said he'll destroy the temple.
他说什么
He said what?
将来没有一块石头是不被拆毁的
Not one stone will be left standing.
他威胁说要拆毁圣殿
He threatens to destroy the temple.
我们必须迅速行动  而且不能声张
We must move swiftly but softly.
我们不能公开抓捕他
We can not arrest him openly,
否则他的拥护者会暴动
or his his supporters will run riot.
不  不能在逾越节  不行
No, not on Passover. No.
不
No.
我们必须在逾越节前夜
We must bring him in quietly...
把他悄悄带过来
at night before Passover.
玛耳曷  你指给我看的
Malchus, what's the name of that
那个追随者叫什么
follower of his that you pointed out to me?
犹达斯  大司祭
Judas, High Priest.
犹达斯  对
Judas. Yes.
把他带到这来见我
Bring him to me... here.
比拉多宅邸
大人
Sir.
我们在吃饭呢
We're eating.
大人  有个犹太人在圣殿里制造麻烦
Sir, a Jew has been causing trouble in the temple.
所以呢
So?
昨天他攻击了兑换银钱的人
Yesterday he attacked the money changers.
今天他又说要拆毁圣殿
Today he says he will destroy the temple.
他有众多拥护者
He has a large number of supporters.
他叫什么
What's his name?
他们称他纳匝肋人耶稣
They call him Jesus of Nazareth.
我的仆人谈起过他
My servants talk about him.
那是盖法的事
He's Caiaphas' business.
但你要密切注意民众的情况
But you keep an eye on the crowds.
若事态失控  我就关闭圣殿
If they start to get out of hand, I'll shut the temple.
管他是不是过节
Festival or no festival.
辣彼
Rabbi.
我是尼苛德摩
I am Nicodemus.
欢迎
Welcome.
我自愿前来
I come here of my own accord.
大司祭并不知情
The High Priest knows nothing of this.
他来这里干嘛
What's he doing here?
显然他不愿意和我们同坐
Surely he doesn't want to sit with us.
犹达斯
Judas.
你那位来自加里肋亚的朋友
Your friend from Galilee
引起了好一阵轰动啊
has caused quite a stir.
没人能否认他有众多追随者
One cannot deny that he has followers,
尤其是一些没怎么受过教育的人
especially amongst the less well-educated element.
但你  犹达斯
But you, Judas-
我倒是很好奇
I'm intrigued.
他
He-
他有一种能力
He has a power.
很难用言语形容
It's hard for me to put into words.
他的能力就是制造麻烦
A power to cause trouble,
引起骚乱
to stir things up.
攻击兑换银钱之人
Attacking money changers.
威胁要拆毁圣殿
Threatening to destroy the temple-
那是我们的至圣所
the Holy of Holies.
如果他真是...
If he were...
人子
the Son of God-
如果
lf.
他会折辱主的圣殿吗
Would he abuse the house of God?
真正的默西亚
The true Messiah...
会团结以色列  而非使其分裂
will unite Israel, not divide it.
你想对他怎么样
What do you want with him?
谈谈而已
Just to talk.
如果罗马人介入此事
If the Romans step in,
你能想象那时的杀戮吗
can you imagine the slaughter?
那将意味着圣殿的毁灭
It will mean the end of the temple,
信仰的毁灭
the end of our faith,
以及国家的终结
the end of our nation.
你想这样吗  犹达斯
Is that what you want, Judas?
犹达斯  你是他的朋友
Judas, you are his friend.
把他带到这来  小心行事
Bring him here... discreetly.
让我们共同阻止这一切
Let us try to stop this...
趁现在还来得及
while we still can.
那我有什么好处
And what's in it for me?
很好
Good.
希望很快就能听到你的好消息
We shall expect to hear from you presently.
他们说你能创造奇迹
They say you can perform miracles,
说你见过天主的国
that you have seen the kingdom of God.
你也能看见天主的国
You can see the kingdom of God.
但你必须重生
But you must be born again.
重生  如何能重生
Born again? How can you be... born again?
你必须获得新生
You must be reborn.
不是你的肉体
Not in the flesh,
而是你的灵魂
but in a spirit.
风随意向那里吹
The wind blows where it wishes.
却不知道风从哪里来
You don't k now where it comes from...
往哪里去
or where it goes.
凡从圣神而生的  就是这样
And so it is when the Spirit enters you.
天主
God...
竟这样爱了世界
so loved the world...
甚至赐下了自己的独生子
that he gave his one and only son.
使凡信他的人
Believe in him,
不至丧亡  反而获得永生
and you will have eternal life.
星期四
逾越节前一天
随着逾越节愈发临近
The closer it gets to Passover,
耶路撒冷局势更加紧张
the tenser it gets in Jerusalem.
就在三十年前
Just 30 years ago,
罗马人在逾越节游行期间杀害了数千人
the Romans killed thousands during Passover demonstrations.
罗马强盗  罗马人渣
Roman thieves! Roman scum!
罗马强盗
Roman thieves!
罗马强盗  罗马人渣
Roman thieves! Roman scum!
罗马人渣
Roman scum!
场面太混乱了
This is a mess.
我必须通知比拉多
I must inform Pilate.
从我担任总督以来
Since I 've been prefect,
你们犹太人多次挑战我耐心的底线
you Jews have tested my patience to breaking point.
现在我已忍无可忍
Now I 'm beyond it.
是的  但是  总督大人
Yes, but, prefect-
我正在说话
I'm speaking.
倘若动乱在明日再次发生
If disturbance took places a day and repeated tomorrow.
我会立即关闭圣殿
I will shut the temple immediately.
逾越节将被取消
There will be no Passover.
整个城市实行宵禁
I will put this city under curfew.
镇压一切叛乱
I will crush any rebellion.
我说得够明白了吗
Do I make myself absolutely clear?
主  我们感谢你
We thank you, Lord,
感谢你创造天地万物
by whose word everything comes to be.
阿们
Amen.
这是我死前  我们一起吃的
This is our last meal together...
最后一餐
before I die.
什么意思
What do you mean?
你们中有一个人要出卖我
I 'm going to be betrayed to my enemies.
我会被逮捕
Arrested...
并处以死刑
and condemned to death.
玛耳曷  犹达斯有什么消息吗
Malchus, any word from Judas?
没有  大司祭
Nothing, High Priest.
我不会再等了
I won't wait any longer.
玛耳曷  我们今晚就把这个假先知抓起来
Malchus, we arrest this false prophet tonight.
我们怎么知道他是假先知
How do we know he is a false prophet?
他符合
Has he fulfilled...
我们经文中所描述的
any of the signs of a true Messiah
真正的默西亚的特征吗
as written in our scriptures?
尼苛德摩  他符合吗
Well, Nicodemus, has he?
他将依据我们的法律受审
He will be tried according to our law.
我们得除掉他  否则罗马人会毁灭一切
We remove this man or the Romans destroy everything.
除掉
Remove?
处死
Execute?
没错  尼苛德摩
Yes, Nicodemus.
用这个乡下人的命
The life of one peasant...
换取犹太民族的未来
for the future of God's nation.
你们心里不要烦乱
Don't be afraid.
你们要信赖天主
Trust in God.
也要信赖我
Trust in me also.
我去的地方  你们知道往那里去的路
You know the way to where I'm going.
我们都不知道你往哪里去
We don't know where you are going,
怎么会知道那条路呢
how can we know the way?
我是道路
I am the way,
真理
the truth...
和生命
and the life.
拿去
Take it.
吃吧
Eat.
这
This-
这是我的身体
This is my body.
这是我的血
This is my blood.
你们这样做
Remember me...
来纪念我
by doing this.
我要去天父那里了
I'm going to the Father.
但我将一直与你们同在
But I will always be with you.
现在我要告诉你们
But now I must tell you...
你们中间有一个人
that one of you here...
要出卖我
will betray me.
是谁
Who?
那个吃了它的人
Whoever eats this.
我不会  我不会出卖你的
I will not. I will not betray you.
快做吧
Do it quickly.
让他走
Let him go.
今夜你们都要跌倒
You will all fall away.
辣彼
Rabbi.
我绝不跌倒
I will not fall away.
我愿意为你舍命
I will lay down my life for you.
你真愿意吗
Will you?
我愿意
I will.
伯多禄
Peter,
我实在告诉你
I tell you...
鸡叫以前
before dawn,
你要三次不认我
you will deny me...three times.
犹达斯  他在哪
Judas. Where is he?
-我...  -你究竟知不知道他在哪
- I... - Do you know where he is now?
我知道他会去哪
I know where he's going.
带我的侍从找到他
Lead my servant to him.
革责玛尼园
醒寤吧
Wake up.
免陷于诱惑
And keep awake.
时辰已到
The time has come.
心神固然切愿  但肉体却软弱
The spirit is willing, but the flesh is weak.
我必须要祈祷
I must pray.
父啊
Father.
我知道
I know...
一切
it must be...
照你所愿意的
as you will it.
父啊  请给我免去这杯吧
Father, take this from me.
宽恕我
Spare me.
主啊  你定会满意我的所为
Lord, I know you will please with me.
因你一直诚心扶持我
For you sustain me in sincerity.
感谢你们  我们的祖先
We thank you, our ancestors,
感谢你们的庇佑
for watching over us.
父啊
Father.
愿上主
Praise the Lord.
以色列天主，受赞颂
God of Israel.
自永远直到永远
Everlasting and everlasting.
阿们， 阿们！（咏41）
Amen and amen.
如果这是你的旨意  父啊
If you will it, Father.
如果这是你的旨意
If you will it,
我必完成
your will...
你的旨意
is mine.
你来做的事 就做吧
Do what you came for.
叛徒
Traitor!
抓住他  抓住他
Take him. Take him.
不
No!
快跑  耶稣
Run, Jesus!
跑  快跑
Run! Run!
快跑  耶稣
Run, Jesus!
伯多禄
Peter.
因为凡持剑的
He who lives by the sword...
必死在剑下
dies by the sword.
快跑
Run!
快点  走  快走
Come on, you! Move! Move it!
把他带回去
Take him back.
这人怎么处置
What about this one?
滚远点
Get out of here!
快来
Come on.
我不会抛下耶稣的
I won't leave Jesus.
-伯多禄  -快走吧
- Peter - Come on!
快走  玛利亚
Come on, Mary.
别停下
Keep moving!
走快点
Quickly!
耶稣
Jesus!
起来
Get up!
够了
Enough!
接着走  别停下
Keep him moving.
叫你口出狂言
We'll teach you to blaspheme.
过来
Come on!
-告诉盖法我们抓到耶稣了  -是
- Tell Caiaphas we have Jesus. - Yes, sir.
你不用跟了
Not you.
"因此夜间的审判包括死刑
"Therefore night trials involving death penalty
不得在安息日前夜
may not be held on the eve of Sabbath...
或是其他宗教节日前夜进行"
or on the eve of a feast day."
大司祭说
The best scholar say
审判只能在白昼进行
we must hold our trials by daylight.
但我们今晚就审判
But the trial is tonight.
你不能这么干
You cannot go through with this.
这不合法
It is not legal.
我们的司祭说
Our scholar say
审判必须在白天在法庭上公开进行
it must be in court, in daylight, in public!
必须这么做
It is necessary.
为什么要这么匆忙？
Why the rush?
你知道的
You know why.
比拉多会关闭圣殿
Pilate will close the temple.
我们必须除掉这个耶稣
We must be rid of this Jesus.
如果他真的是人们所说的那个人呢
But what if he really is who they say he is?
我们会准确地判断这事的
We are to decide precisely that.
现在  按天主指引的做
now, with God's guidance.
天主要求我们遵守法律
God demands we obey the law.
那我提醒你  法律是这么写的
Let me remind you what the law says.
任何对司祭或审判表示蔑视的人
Anyone who shows contempt for the judge or for the priest...
格杀勿论
shall be put to death.
任何人
Anyone.
告诉我
Tell me.
请告诉我
Speak to me.
为什么放任他们如此对你
Why letting them do this to you?
别再向前了  退下
No, no, no. Get back.
看到那个被捕的人了吗
Have you seen the man they arrested?
-看到那个被捕的人了吗  -退下
- Have you seen the man they arrested?  -Get back.
同胞们
Brothers.
感谢各位深夜前来
Thank you for coming at this hour.
如果不是要紧事
You know I would not have asked you...
我也不会如此兴师动众
if it were not so serious.
让他起来
Get him up.
纳匝肋人耶稣
Jesus of Nazareth,
你被指控亵渎天主
you are charged with blasphemy.
玛利亚
Mary?
Mary.
出什么事了  我的儿子呢
What has happened? Where is my son?
耶稣被捕了
Jesus has been arrested.
被捕
Arrested?
但我们不知道他被抓到哪去了
But we don't know where they have taken him.
被捕
Arrested?
在夜里吗
At night?
他们是秘密行动
They want to keep it secret.
不希望引起民众抗议
They don't want any protests.
他利用魔鬼的力量去治愈疾病
He has employed demons... to heal.
他还威胁说
He has threatened...
要摧毁天主的圣殿
to destroy the temple of our Lord.
同胞们  在审判之前
Brothers, we must listen...
我们必须倾听
before we judge.
所以  我请先知来
And so I invite the prophet...
说一说
to speak.
请告诉我们  天主向你传达的话
Tell us the message you bring from God.
没有吗
Nothing?
无话可说吗  当然了
Nothing to say? Surely.
那告诉我们
Tell us this.
你是不是默西亚
Are you... the Chosen One?
你是不是天主之子
Are you the Son of God?
我是
I am.
你们将要看见人子
And you will see me coming...
乘着天上的云彩降来
with the clouds of heaven,
坐在那大能者的右边
sitting at the right hand of God.
真是无法容忍
This is repulsive!
和天主一起  骗子
With God? Impostor!
蠢材  亵渎者
Fool! Blasphemer!
大家都听见了
We have heard enough.
裁决结果只有一个
There is only one verdict.
他有罪吗
Guilty?
这是不对的
This is wrong.
这给我们的公会带来耻辱
This brings shame on our council.
不是吗
Does it not?
同胞们
Brothers.
此人被判处死刑
The sentence is death.
《圣经》下集预告
Next time on The Bible.
长官  我们需要您的帮助
Prefect, we need your help.
我们判决了一名非常危险的犯人
We have convicted a dangerous criminal.
他活一日  就是一日的威胁
He is an immediate threat.
他叫什么
His name.
纳匝肋人耶稣
Jesus of Nazareth.
你是犹太人的君王吗
Are you the king of the Jews?
我的国
My kingdom...
不属于这世界
is not of this world.
此人不过是被人蛊惑了而已
He's guilty of nothing more than being deluded.
他侵犯了我们神圣的法律
He has broken our sacred laws.
纳匝肋人耶稣被判有罪
Jesus of Nazareth has been found guilty.
拿回你们的臭钱吧
Take back your money!
你认识他  你称他辣彼
You know him. You called him Rabbi.
我不认识此人
He's nothing to do with me.
他们会杀了他的
They're going to kill him.
钉死他
Crucify him!
你必因此事后悔终生
You'll live to regret this.
一周之后就没人会记得他是谁了
He'll be forgotten in a week.
你本应是他的磐石
You were supposed to be his rock.
我辜负了他  如今也无法请求他的宽恕
I failed him. Now I can't ask him to forgive me.
父啊
Father.
宽赦他们吧
Forgive them...
因为他们不知道他们做的是什么
for they know not what they do.
如果你想为天主教的影视字幕出一份福传的力量， 请来Q群180574695【天主的译站】指导交流!